Okay, so we're online?
Yeah, you're online.
All right, hi everybody. Welcome to today's דף. daf. We are starting
from נ' עמוד א'. nun amud aleph. We're a little bit behind.
Today's דף daf will be נ"א, nun aleph, but we're picking up
from נ' עמוד א' nun amud aleph by the two dots, three
lines down from where it begins to get wide.
ולא את השולחן אלא
בלחם הפנים בשבת.
Velo et
hashulchan ela
belechem
hapanim beshabbat.
You see it? Yeah. Okay.
Okay, so this is going back to the משנה mishna which mentions
a number of different
items,
shall we say.
I'll just review. Yesterday we discussed the
קטורת, ketoret, שאין מחנכין את המזבח הזהב אלא בקטורת הסמים, she'ein mechanchin
et hamizbe'ach hazahav ela biktores hashamim,
because the way you inaugurate the inner golden מזבח mizbe'ach is with
the קטורת הסמים, ketoret hasamim, and המזבח העולה אלא בתמיד של שחר,
hamizbe'ach ha'olah ela b'tamid shel shachar, and the מזבח העולה mizbe'ach ha'olah
is inaugurated through the תמיד של שחר. tamid shel shachar. And now
we're on to the third part of the list, ולא את השולחן
אלא בלחם הפנים בשבת. Velo et hashulchan ela belechem hapanim beshabbat. So
the way you inaugurate the שולחן shulchan is with the לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, we know that's what it's for, and on שבת. Shabbat.
Okay, so that's what we're discussing now.
Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara is inferring from here by the
fact that it says
שבת, Shabbat, אלא בכל החונכי הוא דלא מחנך הא קדושי מקדש? ela
bechol ha'chunchei hu d'lo mechanech ha kiddushei mekadesh? So
does that seem to imply that on a weekday because it says
the only again, like if you just wanted to look at that
משנה mishna but I'll read it because it says that the way
you are מחנך mechanech this is ולא את השולחן אלא בלחם הפנים
בשבת, velo et hashulchan ela belechem hapanim beshabbat, right? Okay, so
there's
a difference between חנוך, chinuch, which is like kind of inaugurating and
then sanctification, right? So it says you can't sanctify it, I mean
you can't inaugurate it, so maybe אלא בכל החונכי הוא דלא מחנך
הא קדושי מקדש, ela bechol ha'chunchei hu d'lo mechanech ha kiddushei mekadesh,
right? So maybe it won't be inaugurated but maybe you can just
sanctify it on a חול. chol.
So היא גופא קא משמע לן דחנוך וקדוש שולחן בשבת הוא. hi
gufa kamashma lan d'chinuch ve'kiddush shulchan beshabbat hu.
No, no, it's not trying to say that. Don't take an implication,
don't parse your words so much to say that you can kind
of do like a half measure on a חול. chol. That's not
really what it's coming to say. So no, it's coming to tell
you exactly that point, כדתניא סיפא ולא את המנורה אלא בשבעה נרותיה
בין הערבים, k'detanya seifa velo et hamenora ela beshiva neroteiha bein ha'arbayim,
because if you look at the fourth part of the list, it's
mentioning the only way you do the נרות nerot is with, is
the only way you מחנך mechanech the מנורה menora is with the
נרות nerot in the evening time. And obviously the whole point is
as תורה Torah mentions is you light it in the evening time,
don't imply that you can light it during the day. It's not
lit during the day, it's only lit at night. So the point
being that the reason why you can't say it all kind of
comes together. The חנוך chinuch and the קדוש kiddush come together and
that's what it's trying to say.
Don't infer from
the חנוך chinuch that you separate the חנוך chinuch from the קדוש.
kiddush. It comes one and the same and it's kind of an
obvious point. And the reason they both come together is one comes
with the other essentially.
So the קדוש kiddush will do the חנוך. chinuch. So that's why,
since they both come at the same time, you need to wait
till the proper time and the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim we know
was done on שבת Shabbat as the תורה Torah finds.
Now let's go on. תנו רבנן זהו קטורת שעלתה ליחיד המזבח החיצון
הוראת שעה היתה. Tanu rabanan zehu ketoret she'alta leyachid hamizbe'ach hachitzon hora'at
sha'ah hayta.
So now remember
that that's part of why I read the list is that we
inaugurate the המזבח הזהב, hamizbe'ach hazahav, which is synonymous with the המזבח
הקטורת, hamizbe'ach haketoret, it's the same thing and all that was the
inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. So remember, you have your outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, which
is called מזבח עולה, mizbe'ach olah, that's where you bring all your
different קרבנות, korbanot,
except for obviously the ones that are brought inside,
but you don't really bring, you have
חטאת שרפות chatat srefot like on יום כפור Yom Kippur and stuff
like that, but you're not actually offering the entrails on there. But
anyway,
so your outer מזבח mizbe'ach is for most everything, right? And that's
where you bring your מנחות, menachot, you bring all these things, but
the inner מזבח mizbe'ach is actually the המזבח הקטורת, hamizbe'ach haketoret, right?
So that's where you do it, and
that's
the המזבח הזהב. hamizbe'ach hazahav.
Okay, so you say again the קטורת ketoret is in the inner
מזבח, mizbe'ach, not on the outer?
The המזבח הזהב hamizbe'ach hazahav and המזבח הקטורת hamizbe'ach haketoret and
that's the inner one.
That's the inner one. מזבח עולה mizbe'ach olah is the outer one,
that's where you bring all your קרבנות, korbanot, your מנחות. menachot.
Okay, but we just talked about קטורת ketoret on
החיצון. hachitzon.
Anyway, so basically you bring your קטורת ketoret on the inside.
But there was one exception.
And that's what the גמרא Gemara just was saying: זהו קטורת של
יחיד על המזבח החיצון והוראת שעה היתה. zehu ketoret shel yachid al
hamizbeach hachitzon vehora'at sha'ah hayetah. It's kind
of like bringing you
in the middle of
a statement, but זהו קטורת של יחיד על המזבח החיצון והוראת שעה
היתה. zehu ketoret shel yachid al hamizbeach hachitzon vehora'at sha'ah hayetah.
So there was this, again the גמרא's Gemara gonna talk about what's
the this? This was the קטורת ketoret that was for an individual.
Again, the קטורת ketoret that we bring is for the community, right?
Because it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. And it was on the
outer מזבח mizbeach
and that, because that's not what you usually do, was a one-time
thing. Okay, what do you mean היכא? hecha? What is all this
about? אלא בנשיאים. ela binessi'im. Right? So basically when you know we
read all this and so that the נשיאים nesi'im brought this, that,
the other, then כף אחת עשרה זהב מלאה קטורת, kaf achat asarah
zahav mela'ah ketoret, right?
So one of the things they brought was
this כף, kaf, or however you translate that, but call it... you
know, for lack of a better word I'll just generically say it's
a utensil that was filled with this קטורת. ketoret. And this קטורת
ketoret was offered on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. So that is very
unusual. So that was the only time that it was ever done,
right? So the גמרא Gemara is going to parse this and say...
so the implication... so what happened? It was a קרבן יחיד korban
yachid and was brought on the outer altar, right? So what can
we potentially learn from this?
So let's go on: אלא יחיד על מזבח החיצון הוא דלא הא
על מזבח הפנימי מקריב?
ella yachid al mizbeach hachitzon hu d'lo ha al mizbeach
hapnimi makriv?
So okay, so now it says that you know, again
individual קרבן korban and outer. So let's say you switch it. Let's
say it was communal קרבן. korban. If it was communal קרבן, korban,
can we say
that potentially the law is different? And if let's say if you
brought it in the inner versus outer altar, can we say it's
different? So basically what we're saying here is: so maybe it's a
problem bringing it in the מזבח החיצון, mizbeach hachitzon, right? Let's say
יחיד yachid were
to voluntarily decide to give his קטורת. ketoret. Can you bring that
on the inner מזבח mizbeach just like the ציבור tzibbur brings their
קטורת ketoret on the inner מזבח? mizbeach? ובתו על מזבח החיצון דיחיד
לא הא דציבור מקריבו? uvtu al mizbeach hachitzon d'yachid lo ha d'tzibbur
makrevu?
And furthermore, can it only be that it's a problem to offer
it on the מזבח החיצון mizbeach hachitzon for a יחיד? yachid? But
let's say a ציבור, tzibbur, can they if they so choose instead
of bringing it in on the inner one, bring it on the
outer? So basically trying to, you know, have both sides of the
question, right?
So
can that be that anything other than a ציבור tzibbur bringing it
in the inner altar is okay? That's what they're trying to say.
ואתה יכול יהא יחיד מתנדב ומביא כיוצא בה נדבה? ve'atah yakhol yehei
yachid mitnadev u'mevi kayotzei bah nidavah?
So can it possibly be that a יחיד yachid can just offer
it as a voluntary offering? You know we know they did in
the נשיאים, nesi'im, but can it be that for generations, you know,
you can bring your voluntary קרבן, korban, right? That happens all the
time. Want to bring an עולה, olah, go ahead. You want to
bring your שלמים, shelamim, שלמים shelamim are voluntary offerings for individuals. So
maybe you can say, okay, well maybe I can decide to bring
a קטורת ketoret as a voluntary offering. וכל ענייה בה מוצא פיך
תשמור ועשית. v'khol anyah bah motze picha tishmor ve'asita.
And then the end of that is כאשר נדבת לפיך נדבה, ka'asher
nadavta l'fi'cha nidavah, right? So basically we learn from there that you
can do something as a free-willed offering and maybe if you bring
the קטורת ketoret as free-willed offering then go ahead. יכול תהא? yachol
tehei? So תלמוד לומר לא תעלו Talmud lomar lo ta'alu. עליו קטורת
זרה. Ketoret Zara
So
we have to, we say no, you can't do that because when
it talks about the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, the מזבח הקטורת, mizbeach
haketoret, and I'll read the
פסוק pasuk over here
and I'm going to backtrack just a little bit. It's talking about
making... this should be in פרשת תצוה. parshat Tetzaveh. The first פסוק
pasuk over there: ועשית מזבח מקטר קטורת עצי שטים תעשה אתו. ve'asita
mizbeach miktar ketoret atzei shittim ta'aseh oto.
So talking about making the מזבח הקטורת mizbeach haketoret and talks about
its dimensions. And then it says a few פסוקים pesukim later: והקטיר
עליו אהרן קטורת סמים בבקר בבקר בהטיבו את הנרת יקטירנה. vehiktir alav
Aharon ketoret samim baboker baboker beteivo et hanerot yaktirenah. So
אהרן Aharon brings the קטורת ketoret in the morning when he... and
it links it with... and this is going to come into play
a little bit later... it links it with the הטבת הנרות hatavat
hanerot when you... I don't know what the right word for that
is... they prepare them.
They prepare them.
Yeah, I guess that's the best way to say it... when he
cleans... translates it as cleaning the lamps. And then you do it
again in the evening... קטורת תמיד. ketoret tamid. Then לא תעלו עליו
קטורת זרה, lo ta'alu alav ketoret zarah. right? And you cannot offer
this foreign, alien,
whatever, קטורת, ketoret,
and an
עולה olah or a מנחה minchah ונסך לא תסכו עליו. venesach lo
tiskeu alav. So we use it basically for קטורת ketoret is what
it's saying here. And then fine.
So that's what that is. So we're taking it to mean that
קטורת Ketoret. זרה would be anything other than the communal קטורת. Ketoret
So
that won't work. So basically, so basically we nixed the יחיד Yachid
offering a נדבה Nedava on this מזבח הקטורת. Mizbeach Haketoret. So what
do we...
so okay fine. לא יהיה יחיד מביא שאין מביא חובתו כיוצא בה.
Lo yihiyeh yachid meivi she'ein meivi chovato kayotzei bah. Okay fine. So
now we understand that a יחיד Yachid cannot bring his קטורת Ketoret
on the inner one because we don't have any analog for offering
a... for יחיד Yachid offering
offering קטורת Ketoret, at all, right? Again, except for this one-time deal
but we have analogs for קרבנות Korbanot all the time like I
was mentioning, you know, you bring your שלמים Shelamim all the time,
you're giving an עולה Olah all the time. So we don't really
see that you can ever bring קטורת, Ketoret which is why okay,
we've now nixed the bringing the קטורת Ketoret by יחיד Yachid as
a free will offering. אבל מביא ציבור יהא מביא שמביא חובה כיוצא
בה.
Aval meivi tzibur yehei meivi shemeivi chovah
kayotzei bah. So okay fine, so maybe the ציבור Tzibur can, the
community can bring its
קטורת Ketoret on it because
they bring קטורת Ketoret all the time, right? So then maybe maybe
that would work? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar לא תעלו. Lo ta'alu. So
it says no, you can't, that also I read. לא תעלו. Lo
ta'alu You just forget it, you just can't. לא תעלו Lo ta'alu
is a sort of
a categorical statement. לא תעלו Lo ta'alu also is in the plural,
right? So that means that the ציבור Tzibur can't do it either
as רש"י Rashi points out. All right fine. So now we've learned
that
anything other than a
community קטורת Ketoret is invalid on the inner מזבח, Mizbeach, which is
the מזבח הקטורת. Mizbeach Haketoret. But what about the last part of
it? יכול לא יעלו המזבח הפנימי אבל יעלו על המזבח החיצון. Yachol
lo ya'alu hamizbeach hapnimi aval ya'alu al hamizbeach hachitzon.
Okay fine. So maybe you can bring it on the outer altar.
תלמוד לומר את שמן המשחה ואת קטורת הסמים לקודש ככל אשר ציוויתיך
יעשו. Talmud lomar et shemen hamishchah ve'et ketoret hasamim lakodesh kechol asher
tzivitcha ya'asu.
So
later on and
I'll get it right now, I'll read it from here.
So what are we talking about that? What are we suggesting is
not?
What we're suggesting is that we know that you bring the, we
know that the ציבור Tzibur brings its קטורת Ketoret in the מזבח
הזהב, Mizbeach Hazahav, right? So now we said okay, so
maybe the יחיד Yachid can also bring his קטורת Ketoret in the
מזבח הזהב. Mizbeach Hazahav. But no because לא תעלו עליו, Lo ta'alu
alav, right? Okay fine. And we also said from the fact that
it says לא תעלו that the ציבור Tzibur can't do it either,
right? So the one, and we know the יחיד Yachid can't ever
do it because you don't have any analog for on the מזבח
הזהב Mizbeach Hazahav because we don't have any analog for him ever
offering קטורת Ketoret as a נדבה. Nedava. So now maybe the one
thing that's left is ציבור Tzibur bringing on the מזבח
החיצון.
Mizbeach Hachitzon.
Because says לא תעלו עליו Lo ta'alu alav is the ציבור Tzibur
can't bring it on the מזבח הפנימי, Mizbeach Hapnimi, but maybe they
can bring it on מזבח החיצון. Mizbeach Hachitzon. That's where we're at
right
now. We're going to answer it. But the answer is this פסוק
Pasuk which I'm going to read to you. So
it talks about in the very end of פרשת כי תשא. Parashat
Ki Tisa.
God says to משה, Moshe, I have called on בצלאל Betzalel and
he's going to do all these things. It mentions that he's going
to do לעשות בזהב ובכסף ובנחשת La'asot bazahav uvakesef uvanechoshet
and ועשו את כל אשר ציוויתיך. Ve'asu et kol asher tzivitcha. We'll
do whatever I commanded. But then instead of just ending it there,
it says the specifics: the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, the שולחן, Shulchan,
the מזבח הקטורת, Mizbeach Haketoret, and it mentions
the שמן המשחה
וקטורת הסמים,
Shemen Hamishchah Veketoret
Hasamim, then ככל אשר ציוויתיך יעשו. Kechol asher tzivitcha ya'asu. And says
whatever I commanded you they shall do, which is kind of repetitive
because it basic bookends with what He commanded, which is a general
statement. Then it goes into all the specifics, the קטורת Ketoret among
them, then it ends again with saying whatever I commanded. Okay?
So basically what they're saying is from the mere fact
that
it's almost like the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thing: you need to
have a כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal uferat uklal, the אי אתה דן
אלא כעין הפרט, Ei ata dan ela ke'ein haprat, right? So the
mere fact, so since it's bookended by two general things but mentions
things that are very specific, it's come to tell you only these
things. So since in the end it wraps it up with ככל
אשר ציוויתיך יעשו, Kechol asher tzivitcha ya'asu, which is repetitive, then אין
לך אלא מה שאמור בעניין. Ein lecha ela mah she'amur be'inyan. So
it can only be what I mentioned. And I mentioned over there
the מזבח הקטורת Mizbeach Haketoret and that's where you put the קטורת
Ketoret as we know. So therefore it means that's the only thing
you can do it for.
So are we saying that there's...
so we're saying you can't bring, a ציבור Tzibur can't bring it
on the outer מזבח. Mizbeach. And we know the יחיד Yachid can't
offer it at all. So basically what we're saying is the only
place this קטורת Ketoret can be, the only way this קטורת ketoret
can be brought is on מזבח הפנימי Mizbeach Hapnimi by ציבור. Tzibur.
That's our conclusion.
Are we okay with that?
No, just
a
second. I see, so we've rejected, okay, I got it. Okay, so
the outside מזבח mizbe'ach is only מה שאמור בבנין. ma she'amur binyan.
Therefore, the only place for the ציבור tzibur to bring the קטורת
ketoret. is the inside
מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Right. Or actually the other way around, that the only מה שאמור
בבנין ma she'amur binyan is referring to the inside מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Because, yeah, because
it has מזבח הקטורת mizbe'ach haketoret as part of the
list. ומה שאמור בבנין vema she'amur binyan is referring to that.
So then how haven't we excluded both then? So there's no place
for the ציבור tzibur to bring their קטורת.
ketoret No, because it says מזבח הקטורת. mizbe'ach haketoret.
That's the inside one. That's right.
We're trying to say, can they bring on the outside? We said
no because אין לך אלא מה שאמור בבנין ein lach ela ma
she'amur bebinyan and the ענין inyan was they do מזבח הקטורת. mizbe'ach
haketoret.
It's specifically designated that
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Right, okay, yeah. Specially for... Not the other one. So
that's the gold one, so that's the gold מזבח. mizbe'ach.
The inside one, yeah.
Inside is the gold מזבח. mizbe'ach.
There's no...
Okay, yeah, so it excludes the other one that people to bring...
Okay, I never heard of a... of a קרבן korban of a
ציבור tzibur of a נדבה nedavah of the ציבור. tzibur.
עולת
קיץ המזבח,
olat kaitz
hamizbe'ach, right? How's that?
עולת קיץ
המזבח.
olat
kaitz
hamizbe'ach.
Is that what that is?
No, I'm saying isn't that a קרבן נדבה korban nedavah of the
ציבור? tzibur?
But that's like...
No, but we're saying that maybe... yeah, I think what we're aiming,
we're not saying can the ציבור tzibur bring the קטורת ketoret as
a נדבה, nedavah, we're saying maybe they can do their חובה chovah
on the outer one.
I think, right? אבל ציבור יהיו מביא שיביא. aval tzibur yehu mevi
sheyavi.
That's what I think we're saying.
But anyway, we're just saying that, you know, but anyway, we're saying
that either way,
what would be the הוה אמינא? hava amina? No, I don't think
so. What would be the הוה אמינא hava amina to bring the
קטורת ketoret that the תורה Torah tells you to bring on the
מזבח הקטורת, mizbe'ach haketoret, I don't... I'm sorry, what's the הוה אמינא
hava amina that the daily קטורת ketoret would be on the outside
מזבח? mizbe'ach?
Well,
they are saying that maybe,
maybe the ציבור tzibur could, the תורה Torah doesn't exclude that, the
תורה Torah says explicitly, bring it on the מזבח הקטורת. mizbe'ach haketoret.
Yeah, but look how we started. Yeah, look how we started. ותו
במזבח חיצון יחיד הוא דלא הציבור מקרבו. vetu bemizbe'ach chitzon yachid hu
delo hatzibur mikrebu.
Where are you, sir?
I'm just on נ"ט עמוד א', nun tet amud alef, three lines
from the bottom.
Yeah. ותו במזבח
חיצון
יחיד הוא דלא הציבור
מקרבו.
vetu bemizbe'ach chitzon yachid hu
delo
hatzibur
mikrebu. That's a great question. That's for נדבה. nedavah.
We're asking about נדבה. nedavah.
So, I'm sorry, what are you trying to say? You're saying
that...
I
forgot... No, yeah, I'm just asking. I never... I never heard of
a... of the ציבור tzibur bringing a נדבה. nedavah.
For קטורת ketoret or for anything else? For anything. Right, and then
I'm saying, don't you think that the עולת קיץ המזבח olat kaitz
hamizbe'ach is essentially a נדבה? nedavah?
I see. Okay. Okay, so how do they say? They say the
הוה אמינא hava amina is
that the ציבור tzibur could maybe be bringing as a נדבה nedavah
מזבח חיצון, mizbe'ach chitzon, or are they saying that the ציבור tzibur
can just decide to even do their חובה chovah מזבח חיצון? mizbe'ach
chitzon? How are they translating it there? I'm just, just since we're
on that
topic. נ"ט עמוד א', nun tet amud alef, three lines from the
bottom.
It could be thought that any private individual may vow to bring
a נדבה nedavah offering, an offering like that, oops, sorry. Any rate,
the congregation may offer up incense either on the
other also.
So
they're saying that the הוה אמינא hava amina is for even their
obligation or for their נדבה. nedavah. Doesn't specify. Right. So anyway, at
any rate, but you know, but אין לך אלא מה שאמור בבנין
ein lach ela ma she'amur bebinyan seems to be pretty clear. The
only way you can do it is, is
inside as an obligation. That's, that's essentially the conclusion.
I'm just curious, like how does that work? How does the ציבור
tzibur decide to bring a voluntary
קטורת ketoret offering?
Well, we're saying you can't. We're saying you can't.
You can not. Right.
But what were they
saying,
you can do it on the inside מזבח? mizbe'ach?
No, אין לך אלא מה שאמור בבנין ein lach ela ma she'amur
bebinyan is the חובה chovah for the ציבור. tzibur.
Now you're confusing me.
Yeah.
Because this whole thing was for the חובה, chovah, right? I mean,
they're not talking, this whole part about constructing the משכן mishkan was
not saying that, you know, we're constructing it for a יחיד yachid
to do his נדבה. nedavah. Yeah, yeah, of course. So, so אין
לך אלא מה שאמור בבנין ein lach ela ma she'amur bebinyan is,
I mean, if you just want to get it, you know, you
can even distill the whole thing just to that. The only thing
in אמור בבנין amur bebinyan is מזבח הקטורת, mizbe'ach haketoret, which it
mentions specifically, and the קטורת ketoret which is brought on it, which
is also mentioned. And, and מה שאמור בבנין ma she'amur bebinyan is
that's what it's for. The inner, the inner מזבח mizbe'ach is for
the קטורת ketoret. that's brought as an obligation by the community.
Oh, so then... so there is no place for the... for the
ציבור tzibur to bring a voluntary קטורת. Ketoret Oh, that's what I
said before. Okay. That's what I've been trying to say before.
Okay. Yeah. Okay, or maybe I wasn't understanding what you were trying
to say then. But, but anyway, so our point being, so why
do we go through all that? So now... So now we minimize
everything other than as we said, the ציבור Tzibbur bringing it in
as an obligation. Right? That's the only thing they can do. They
can only bring it as an obligation and they can only bring
it on the מזבח הקטורת, Mizbeach Haketoret, which is the מזבח הזהב.
Mizbeach Hazahav. So now, but what we were trying, what we were
trying to do is from the fact that it says, you know,
that the way we started this was this is a קטורת that
was for the יחיד Yachid on מזבח החיצון. Mizbeach Hachitzon. Right? So
we're trying to say that, you know, anything else may be okay,
right? So then which is it? We just got through saying that
nothing is okay, but then the implication was that something else may
be okay from that הוראת שעה. Hora'at Sha'ah. So the answer is
kind of obvious, again, that לא מבעיא, Lo Mibaya, it's basically, it's
basically of course לא מבעיא קאמר. Lo Mibaya Ka'amar. לא מבעיא ציבור
על מזבח חיצון דלא אשכחן. Lo Mibaya Tzibbur al Mizbeach Hachitzon delo
Ashkachan. You know, we understand that you definitely can't bring the, the
ציבור Tzibbur cannot bring it on the outer מזבח Mizbeach because we
never see that they can bring it on the outer מזבח. Mizbeach.
ולא מבעיא יחיד על מזבח הפנימי דלא אשכחן. Velo Mibaya Yachid al
Mizbeach Hapnimi delo Ashkachan. And and it also certainly, you know, goes
without saying essentially that a יחיד Yachid can't bring it on the
inner one because again, we see that they can never do it.
אלא אפילו יחיד על מזבח החיצון, Ela afilu Yachid al Mizbeach Hachitzon,
right? But even a יחיד Yachid can't bring it as a voluntary
offering on מזבח חיצון Mizbeach Hachitzon because we did see דאשכחן בניסין,
De'ashkachan Binisin, because we did see that that happened in the נשיאים.
Nesi'im. Why not? Because הוראת שעה היתה, Hora'at Sha'ah Hayta, right? Which
implies anything other than that can't happen. Okay? We good? Yeah. Alright.
Let's see. I'll get,
I'll mess with the little book, I'll do it later. Alright fine.
You know what, actually let's read this now. The חביתין, Chavitin, the
now new משנה. Mishnah. The חביתין Chavitin were for lack of a
better word I'm going to call them pancakes. But that was a
special מנחה Mincha and I'm going to read you the פסוק, Pasuk,
well part of a פסוק. Pasuk. Where did they say this was?
Because I don't have the version that says where these פסוקים Pesukim
are. It's in ויקרא, Vayikra, right?
There are two places it's mentioned I think. Do you have like
the little, like you know you have the פסוקים Pesukim on the
side? Can you tell me where that was?
Which one? Sorry.
Where we're about to say the
חביתין. Chavitin.
ויקרא ו. Vayikra Vav.
בפרשת צו, B'parashat Tzav, right?
מהגמרא דמנחות
דף י"ג.
Mehagmarah
d'Menachot daf yud gimmel.
Okay. So this is what we're talking about. That, I'm just going
to read it and we're going to, the גמרא's Gemara going to
really talk about it. I'm going to read the first two פסוקים
Pesukim and then they're going to read the others later when we
get up to it. וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר, Vayedaber Hashem el
Moshe Lemor, that's the first one. So the second one is זה
קרבן אהרן ובניו, Zeh Korban Aharon uvanav, this is the קרבן Korban
and the גמרא's Gemara going to really talk about this, of אהרן
Aharon and his children אשר יקריבו לה' Asher yakrivu l'Hashem that they
will offer to ה', Hashem, ביום המשח אתו. B'yom himashach oto. This
is again, remember all this is the inauguration of the משכן. Mishkan.
עשירית האפה סלת מנחה תמיד, Asirit ha'ephah solet mincha tamid, so a
tenth of an איפה, Ephah,
סולת, Solet, this will be a תמיד. Tamid. מחציתה בבקר ומחציתה בערב,
Machatzitah baboker umachatzitah ba'erev,
so half of it is in the morning and half of it
is in the evening, right?
And then they're going to get to the rest of it when
the גמרא Gemara gets up to it. So again, it's an עומר
Omer but עומר Omer is basically an עשירית האפה. Asirit ha'ephah. And
half of, you know, first so it mentions it together as an
עומר, Omer, right? It doesn't say half an עומר, Omer, it doesn't
just say half an עומר Omer in the morning, half an עומר
Omer at night, right? It says an עומר, Omer, half of it
in the morning, half of it at night, right? So it's very
important for what we're going to talk about. חביתי כהן גדול לא
היו באין חציין, Chavitei Kohen Gadol lo hayu ba'in chatzayin, right? You
can't bring it, I mean you do offer half and half but
you don't start out by offering it in halves.
So this סולת Solet is called חביתי? Chavitei?
Well this is a type of מנחה, Mincha, it's חביטין. Chavitin. We'll
get into how it's made a little bit later. So you know,
since the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about it. Okay.
Yeah, well the next פסוק Pasuk is על מחבת, Al machavat, on
a pan.
Wait well there's more than that too. But you got, but that's
why it's called the חביטין Chavitin because it's, yeah the next פסוק
Pasuk is על מחבת. Al machavat. But we'll get to that. So
I'm only,
that's what I was kind of debating as to whether to read
it all now but I don't want to confuse everybody. So it
was not, although as I said, you end up offering half in
the morning and half in the night, but you don't start out
with halves. So the גמרא's Gemara going to explain what we mean
by this. אלא מביא עשרון שלם וחוצהו, Ela mevi asaron shalem v'chotzehu,
right? So the משנה Mishnah says you bring a full עשרון Asaron
and then you
half it. מקריב מחצה בבקר ומחצה בין הערבים, Makriv mechtzah baboker u'mechtzah
bein ha'arbayim, so half in the morning, half at
night. Okay, כהן שמביא מחצה שחרית ומת, Kohen shemevi mechtzah shacharit u'met,
right? Okay so the כהן, Kohen, so let's say this is the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because we know that he has to, we
know that there are two times that this is brought. This is
brought for a כהן Kohen
every time he's first starting. So you know, let's say you're the
junior כהן, Kohen, you know I mean let's say you're the apprentice,
right? And now it's your first day on the job, right? So
you bring this. And then now let's say you're the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, right? The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings it every day.
As a matter of fact, and let's say it's the first day
as a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, then he'll bring a double portion.
We'll bring because now it's the first time he's inaugurated as a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and also he's the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So he needs to
bring it. Okay so
now we know that you have to bring it. So since it
starts out by saying it's like a unit, right? You bring an
עשרון issaron or an איפה, ephah, right? It has to, so it's
one unit, which which is half. So let's say he died between
the first and the second one, right? So now what do you
do?
המביא מחצה שחרית ומת ימנו כהן אחר תחתיו. mevi mechtzah shacharit umet
yeminu kohen acher tachtav. So now and now and now
there's a new כהן. kohen. So he'll take over the evening shift
let's say, right?
So should he bring, you know, look, should he bring half? Should
he bring a whole? Should he not do anything? What should he
do?
You talking about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol still? Yes. The new
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol now, right? So there's the old one who
died, now
there's a new one that's there.
But when it says מביא מחצה שחרית, mevi mechtzah shacharit, they don't
really mean מביא, mevi, they mean מקריב. makriv. No, it says...
it says מקריב... makriv... oh right.
But he had to bring the whole the whole unit and he
just used half of it.
Well, he used... he used the whole thing but he used
half of it in the morning, half
of it
at night.
Right? He only got the chance,
even though it says he brought half.
Right, it's not exact, right? Yes. Okay, so anyway the first part.
Was there a minimum half? In other words, could you say let's
say it's four ounces, he had to
bring a unit of
two ounces, then those
four
remaining you could bring at the other time? No, he brought four
ounces... he brought... the whole the day's קרבן korban was four ounces.
Exactly. Two of which was brought in the morning and two of
which was...
I mean you brought all four at the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Then then
he puts it in a... whatever whatever it's put in. The משנה
mishnah should not have said מביא מחצה שחרית, mevi mechtzah shacharit, it
should have said מקריב מחצה שחרית. makriv mechtzah shacharit. But that's the
first part. Right. But that's the first...
but I guess the first part already said מקריב מחצה בבוקר.
makriv mechtzah baboker. You're right.
I mean the second line of the משנה mishnah is מקריב מחצה
בבוקר ומחצה בין הערביים. makriv mechtzah baboker mechtzah bein ha'arbayim. So... But
did the minimum have to be given whatever... Right. Okay. So anyway,
this כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
you know, was alive
in the morning, brought his... brought it, half of it was offered,
and now the new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol takes over from him.
Okay? So now what does he do? לא יביא חצי עשרון מביתו
או חצי עשרונו של ראשון,
lo yavi chatzi issaron mibeto o chatzi issarono
shel rishon, right? So don't... he shouldn't, you know, bring the other
half from his... he's a new כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so don't
say like, okay, well, you know, the first guy took care of
his part, I'll take care of my
part from my funds, because it's supposed to come
from his funds, it's not a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur so to
speak. Isn't it... isn't it presumably the son of the one who
died? Well we'll get to that too, but that's... that's another משנה.
mishnah. So if we get up to it on דף עמוד ב.
daf amud bet. But so anyway, so we don't...
so now what do you do, right? Again, the three possibilities: don't
do anything, bring your full עשרון, issaron, or bring half an עשרון
issaron of your own, or bring the other half of the first
guy. So right? So don't... don't bring half an עשרון issaron from
your house, or חצי עשרונו של ראשון, chatzi issarono shel rishon, don't
bring the other half of the first guy's, אלא מביא עשרון שלם
וחוצהו, ela mevi issaron shalem vechotzehu, right? So... so what happened? מקריב
מחצה ומחצה אבד נמצא שני חצאין קרבים ושני חצאין אובדין, makriv mechtzah
vemechtzah avad nimtza shenei chatza'in krevim ve-shenei chatza'in ovdin, right? So essentially
what happens is that day, like you have two עשרונות issaronot brought,
right? Half of it is brought by the first guy who couldn't...
who couldn't bring the other half because he died, then the new
guy brings a full עשרון issaron and then half of it is
brought for his part. So then the second half of the first
guy's קרבן korban and the second half of the second guy's
קרבן korban just... wasted. The גמרא Gemara will talk about what happens.
But basically it's אובדין, ovdin, I mean the משנה mishnah says it's,
you know, essentially wasted. I don't want to say wasted, but it's...
you know...
disposed of. It's not like an אבידה aveida in that sense, it's
just destroyed, it's certainly not used. Okay, fine. So
they're going to analyze this, and תנו רבנן tenu rabanan and this
is basically what I said, but from the פסוקים. pesukim. תנו רבנן
אילו נאמר מנחה מחצית הייתי אומר מביא
חצי עשרונו מביתו. tenu rabanan ilu ne'emar mincha machatzit hayiti omer mevi
chatzi issarono mibeto. If it would have said... it says מחצית, machatzit,
right? If it would have just said סולת מנחה מחצית, solet mincha
machatzit, right? Half of a סולת solet essentially, then הייתי אומר מביא
חצי עשרונו מביתו שחרית ומקריב וחצי עשרונו מביתו ערבית ומקריב.
hayiti omer mevi chatzi issarono mibeto
shacharit umakriv ve-chatzi issarono mibeto arvit umakriv.
Then you would have thought you initially bring it in halves.
תלמוד לומר מחציתה, Talmud lomar machatzitah,
half of it, which means half of a whole, right? מחציתה בבוקר
ומחציתה בערב.
machatzitah
baboker u-machatzitah ba'erev.
So מחצי משלם הוא מקריב. me-chatzi meshalem hu makriv.
So he brings like a half of a full one. הא כיצד
מביא עשרון שלם וחוצהו מקריב מחצה בבוקר ומחצה בין הערביים, ha keitzad
mevi issaron shalem vechotzehu makriv mechtzah baboker u-mechtzah bein ha'arbayim, which is
what we said. So you bring a... you know, you start out
with a full one, you know, then half of it is offered
in the morning, half of it is offered at night. And then
נטמא מחצה של בין הערביים או שאבד... nitma mechtzah she-bein ha'arbayim o
she-avad...
let's say what happens if the half is lost or rather if
the half is נטמא, nitma, the half becomes טמא tameh somehow or
gets
lost? same thing, same thing. מה ששלמים Ma she-shelemim
הוא מביא. hu mevi. No, because we just said before it has
to be half of a whole. So you can't just go and
start out with another half if the first half got lost. So,
כיצד? מביא עישרון שלם וחוציהו ומקריב מחציה ומחציה אבד. keitzad mevi isaron
shalem v'chotziehu umakriv mechatzya u'mechatzya avad. ונמצאו שני חציין קרבים שני חציין
אובדין, V'nimtzu shnei chatzayan krevim shnei chatzayan ovdin,
like we just like we just said. So basically, so you know,
so let's say again you started out a whole one in the
morning, then then you brought the first one. This is not a
case where he died, you know, this is the case where it
became טמא tamei or got lost, right? So
you gotta bring up another full עישרון isaron at night and then
you bring half of it. So again, same same thing as before.
You bring end up bringing a full עישרון, isaron, right, but but
it ends up coming from two עשרונות. isronot. You're I mean you
end up offering I should say a full עישרון, isaron, but you
end up bringing two of them, right? Because in the morning you
bought a full one, half of it got lost, and in the
evening you brought a full one, half of it you don't use.
Makes sense? Okay. תניא כהן גדול שמת והושיבו אחר תחתיו Tanya kohen
gadol shemet v'hoshivu acher tachtav which is our which is which is
our case in the משנה, Mishna, הביאו אחר תחתיו, Hevi'u acher tachtav,
same thing. יכול יביא חצי עישרון מביתו וחצי עישרון של ראשון? Yakhol
yavi chetzi isaron mi-beito v'chetzi isaron shel rishon? Maybe this new כהן
גדול kohen gadol brings just half from his house or just brings
the other half of the first guy? תלמוד לומר
מחציתה בערב. Talmud lomar machatzita ba'erev. מחצה משלם הוא מביא ומקריב. Mechetza
mishalem hu mevi umakriv. So no, because it says מחציתה, machatzita, which
means half of a whole one, so you have to bring a
half of a whole thing. So... What?
So it's a quar... so three quarters is given of the whole
originally four ounces of the...
How are you getting that?
The the remainder two of the of the dead כהן, kohen, you
divide you split that into two?
He already split into two because he
bought it in the morning.
Yeah, but then what do you do for the remaining four ounces?
It has to be split again.
Why does it have to be split again? Because if...
We're talking about we're talking about someone who's able to offer half
of it and then died. Or offer half of it and then
became טמא. tamei. But you've an interesting question, let's say he brought
the whole thing and then died before offering any of it, right?
Then what would happen? We didn't talk about that but presumably you
couldn't, you know, that the whole thing would go to waste because
it's his personal קרבן korban anyway.
But but doesn't it transfer from כהן kohen to another כהן? kohen?
No, that's what we just said, you can't because like I can't
I can't bring, you know, just like let's say the כהן גדול
kohen gadol dies after offering his after offering half of it, the
this new guy can't bring the the second half.
Who brings it then? Who knows? That's the next משנה, Mishna, his
son.
Hmm. But
presumably not.
But או בנו של או מה שזה לא יהיה?
o bno
shel
o ma sheze lo yiheye?
No, nothing to do with that. But because if he's... But you
know what, let's just wait till the next משנה. Mishna.
Yeah, definitely better to try and get.
But but anyway, so basically it's the same thing. So you know
half becomes טמא tamei or if the guy dies, you know, you
can't bring the other half of the first guy's because it has
to be, you know, because and you can't and you don't bring
and you don't bring just half of your own, because you have
to bring half of a whole one, so כיצד Keitzad?
מביא עישרון שלם וחוציהו ומקריב
מחציה ומחציה אבד.
Mevi isaron shalem v'chotziehu umakriv
mechatzya u'mechatzya avad. ונמצאו שני חציין אובדין שני חציין קרבין. V'nimtzu shnei
chatzayan ovdin shnei chatzayan krevim.
So basically, you know, you're bringing two
עשרונות isronot and then out of that a whole עישרון isaron is
bought and a whole עישרון isaron is is lost, but from different
halves so to speak. Makes sense? Yeah. Okay. Alright
fine. תני קמיה דרב נחמן. Tani kamei d'Rav Nachman.
Now... let me look up one. Okay, מחצה ראשון ומחצה שני תעובר
צורתן ויצאו לבית השריפה. Mechetza rishon u'mechetza sheni te'ubar tzurtan v'yeitz'u l'beit
ha-sreifa. So basically we we said that half of it gets destroyed.
So how does that work? So the first the first part is
is
brought,
as we know, but then the other part תעובר צורתן te'ubar tzurtan
basically means לינה. lina. I mean that's just a way...
תעובר צורתן Te'ubar tzurtan means it kind of like changes its appearance,
which is more of an analogue for meat because if you see
meat overnight then it really would change its appearance. So you know
we're just talking about a flour offering changes its appearance, we're borrowing
the term. So תעובר צורתן te'ubar tzurtan basically means you know so
תעובר צורתן te'ubar tzurtan means like let it like I don't you
know to be nice about it, let kind of like let it
almost like rot so to speak. But but you know...
Not gonna rot, it's gonna get stale.
No no no I know, but no, for meat meat would kind
of like rot. No refrigeration. So again, just borrowing the term. So
so basically what we're saying is תעובר צורתן te'ubar tzurtan means let
it stay overnight. Let it spoil but you know but the way
that was done practically was was you know let it stay overnight.
So and then ויצאו לבית השריפה. v'yeitz'u l'beit ha-sreifa. So
okay
and then the other, you know, so basically after staying overnight, then
it has to be burnt. So
and I'm sorry also מחצה ראשון. mechetza rishon. So
the
what was the רש"י Rashi on this? One second.
Right, so מחצה ראשון mechetza rishon is is the half of the
that comes from the first
ראשון. rishon. to the first כהן, kohein, right? So again, remember the
case where the
כהן גדול kohein gadol died, so his second half isn't isn't brought,
right, and the new כהן kohein brings his full עשרון ezron and
again only you only only half of it, right?
So both both so both of them, so both of them stay
overnight, these halves which aren't brought stay, sorry I kind of mis-translated
it when I said it initially, these these
all both of these halves stay overnight and then then they are
to the בית השריפה. beis hasereifah. So אמר רב נחמן בר שלמה,
Amar Rav Nachman bar Shlomo, ראשון rishon יחזור לצורה, yachazor litzurah, אלא
שני, ela sheini, ואמר ליה, v'amar lei, עיבור צורה מעיקרא איבעי ליה.
ibur tzurah me'ikara ibei lei.
So I understand that the first one he's saying is, you know,
you need to sort of, you know, wait so to speak because
originally, you know, he didn't know he was going to die. So
you know, he presumably, so he brought the whole thing, right, and
you know, each half was going to be offered, right? So I
understand why you need to let something happen to it. But by
the time the second guy comes around to the evening, you only
know he's going to offer a half because it's the evening, right?
So why can't he just burn the second half of the second
guy's מנחה mincha right away, right? It was never going to be
offered.
So he's saying why should he bring the whole one?
No, why should you have to wait overnight? You can't be, you
know, we know he has to bring a whole one because you
have to bring half of a whole. But why do you have
to wait overnight for it to become invalid? We know it was
never going to be offered, basically it was never going to be
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so why do you need to have something
go wrong with it?
That's to be consistent with what initially started off as a whole
and it one becomes automatically valid because the first was given already
in the morning.
But the person was from a different person.
Yeah, but still it was given the same kind.
We're not worried about the kind, we're worrying about, you know, it
goes on the person, and it goes a half of a whole
too. That's the important part, right? In other words, I have to
give half of a whole. So if I'm coming, I can't, you
know, I have to bring a whole, right?
It has to be half of my whole, right? Can't be half
of your whole. So I take both of these together, if I'm
coming in the evening I have to bring a whole one for
half of it. Right, so again, so the question
is but superfluous if I'm giving a half that I don't have
to give is essentially being wasted.
Exactly what we're saying, half of it is wasted. But the question
is but now the question is we know it's going to be
wasted, so the first one I understand why we need to have
something come go on to it because it would have been offered
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So we need to have it like be
invalidated to burn it. But the second one would never go on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so it was never valid, so why wait overnight
to invalidate it? Just burn it right away. That's our question. אלא
שני למה לי עיבור צורה מעיקרא איבעי ליה.
ela sheini lamah li ibur tzurah me'ikara
ibei lei. דאמרה לך מני תנא דבי רבה בר אבוה הוא, d'amrah
lach mani tanna d'bei Rabbah bar Avuha hu, דאמר אפילו פיגול טעון
עיבור צורה, d'amar afilu pigul taun ibur tzurah,
just like, yeah, fine, אי נמי ina hami because even פיגול pigul
which we know is already not going to go on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, it needs to stay overnight. So too this other half of
the second guy's כהן's, kohein the second כהן's kohein מנחה mincha was
never going to go on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, just like פיגול pigul
needs to go overnight on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so too does this.
Basically that's the law. Anything you're going to need to burn has
to be overnight first. That's basically what we're saying. ורש"י אמר אפילו
תימא רבנן. v'Rashi amar afilu teima rabbanan. So רש"י Rashi says even
according to רבנן rabbanan because this is a debated statement whether פיגול
pigul needs to be stayed overnight because רבנן rabbanan says you burn
it right away. So even if רבנן rabbanan that says you burn
פיגול pigul right away says כיון דביניה דפלגי בהו אי בעי האי
מקריב ואי בעי האי מקריב מחזי חזו. keivan d'veinei d'palgi behu i
ba'ei hai makriv v'i ba'ei hai makriv machazi chazu. He's like don't
forget, you know, like when the second כהן kohein
again our question was never on the first כהן's kohein half because,
you know, we know that stay overnight. But on the second כהן's
kohein מנחה mincha why does it have to stay overnight? Half of
it was never going to be מקריב. makriv. Yeah, but which half
was never going to be מקריב? makriv? I start off with a
full עומר, omer, I divide it in half, well I can take
this half, I can take that half. I don't offer the whole
thing, but I can offer either of those halves. So since I
can offer either of those halves, so essentially either of it
was call it, you know, almost designated or I don't know what
the right word is, but you know potentially potentially either
half for the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So since I only took this half
but I could have taken the other half, so since either of
them could have been on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so it's, you know,
the מזבח mizbe'ach like kind of תופס tofes it, you know, kind
of like attached to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So therefore it needs to
stay overnight.
Alright, so now we're going to get into, oh boy, I have
to read actually catch up entirely. So let's let's go on for
the חביתין. chavitin.
I started by saying with the the first two פסוקים psukim and
now I'm going to read the rest of it. על מחבת al
machavat
this is this same
מנחה, mincha, על מחבת בשמן תעשה מורבכת תביאנה תפיני מנחת פתים תקריב
ריח ניחוח לה'. al machavat bashemen te'aseh murbechet tevi'ena tufinei minchat pitim
takriv rei'ach nichoach l'Hashem. So there's a lot of things that go
on here.
מחבת machavat is the frying pan. בשמן תעשה
מורבכת
bashemen te'aseh
murbechet is scalded.
Then תפיני tufinei is baked. מנחת פתים minchat pitim is when you
do פתות אותה פתים patos otah pitim is when you fold it.
So this is kind of hard to understand. I will show you
a picture
which makes it a lot easier.
You're not going to show all the steps but what they're going
to show is the different things. So this, so again, there are
three things. Remember I said fried, baked, and scalded. Or actually, if
you look at the order in the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*, fried, scalded,
and baked. That's what it says. That's the order. Fried. So this
is the fried. Right, this is your מחבת machavat *machvat*. This is
your pan. Can everyone see this?
Oh happened in a second. I want to make sure I get
that in there. So this is one second. So this is the
fried, this is the scalded, and this is the baked.
Okay.
So fried is in the frying pan, scalded you boil it in
and scalded you pour water on. Yeah. And then baked is baked
in an oven. That's that's the way their ovens were back then.
Alright. So now the question is going to be
which is the order? I mean
so
now I'm thinking what do you mean what's the order? I mean
the תורה Torah *Torah* says an order, right? But if you think
about it,
it wouldn't make much sense to scald it in the middle, right?
Because again the תורה *Torah* says fried, scalded, and baked. But if
you fry it and you pour water on it, it's gonna turn
to mush.
Does somebody eat this? What happens to it?
Well that's the next part since you asked. וכל מנחת כהן kohen,
גדול תהיה כליל לא תאכל *Vekhol minchat kohen gadol tihiyeh chalil lo
tei'achel*. לא תאכל *Lo tei'achel*.
So it doesn't really matter it doesn't have to be edible. It
doesn't matter, you could burn it, you could...
Well it's not eaten but you think that I mean if you
pour boiling water on something before after it was already made into...
When you're frying something and you pour water in it's going to
make such a splatter and...
Right that's my point. So that's why because we're going to get
into a debate right now what the order is. So my question
is why would you even debate it? I mean the תורה *Torah*
gave you an order, why why do you think otherwise? But my
point is I think they're saying that if you just think about
it, and none of this is mentioned, this is just my if
anyone has a better explanation on this...
How does he translate תופיני Tufinei *tufinei*?
תופיני Tufinei
*tufinei* we're going to get into that but basically repeatedly
repeatedly baked. תופיני Tufinei *tufinei*.
Where's the baking in the first place in the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*?
That's what תופיני Tufinei *tufinei* is.
Okay.
אפות *Afot* is to bake...
No,
תופיני Tufinei *tufinei* is
אפויות תפויות *afuyot tufoyot* הרבה *harbe*. But we're going to get to
that. We're just going to talk about it. So don't worry about
it.
Do you have a choice when you give it or is it
ritually described, in other words... What's that? When you want to give
a קרבן korban *korban*, do you have a choice of doing any
one of these three?
No, this is all three for one of these for this כהן'ס
חביתין chavitin *kohen's chavitin*. You have to do all three of these
steps.
For all these steps, they don't have a choice?
Right. Okay. So no one is taking... again we're going to get
into a debate as to what the order is, is it baked
before fried or fried before baked. But no one is saying that
then the question is what happens to the scalding part? They're not
addressing that, although רש"י Rashi *Rashi* seems to say that they are,
but but it's not true, but it's probably a misprint in רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*. But so...
so
the question is when does the water come? So if again we're
going to get into a debate, no one's going to... they're not
mentioning the water, so the debate is going to be baked and
fried or fried and baked, right? So when will the water come?
So I would say it happened in one of two places, it
happened before it all or after it all, right? After fried and
baked then you put some water on it. I would say probably
makes sense to have it first because again if you pour water
after it's fried and baked it's going to turn to mush, right?
And and actually this is what we have over here, in this
over here. The the water comes first. I mean logically it would...
But you could have the water in the middle.
Well, the תורה *Torah* mentions the water in the middle, but what
I'm saying is it wouldn't make
sense really because after you've done something to it then to pour
water on it it's going to turn to mush, right? If you
pour water on your bread it's not going to be too nice.
How do you make bagels? No you
boil them
first.
You boil it first and then they're not like fried and baked
before you boil it.
Yeah
but then you fry it, you pour water and then you put
it in the oven.
Well that's what it says.
So so that's possible.
I guess but I mean I don't know I'm just hypothesizing.
Nobody's going to eat it anyway.
But I know but then we're going to also get into it
that it should be nice when you offer it.
It's like about frying an egg. Right. If you would then pour
some water, I'm not saying to drown it in water, but you
pour a little water and then put the whole thing in the
oven.
It's doable. There's nothing horrible about that.
Yeah but first of all I'm not
sure it's I think this actually this thing is actually boiled in
water potentially.
So it's not actually pouring water on it. But even if you
do I don't know how much water it would be and this
is not an egg this is like flour or starting out as
flour. Then you get like mushy I don't think it'd be too
nice if you poured if you poured water on it.
But once you're going to bake it afterwards it'll it'll have a
shape. It wouldn't be... I guess if you pour it into a
pot or a pan or whatever.
I know and in this משנה where it's just this me hypothesize.
Okay. I mean it probably wouldn't be as good you
know but no one is eating it so...
No one's eating it but... No but it has to be nice
for the offering for something else.
Offered means it gets burnt?
No offered on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Burnt. Burnt. Oh yeah I mean
eventually you put it on the fire.
So it'll be burnt. Right.
Right. Right. Okay anyway
now that we had this background. Okay I'll just start from תודות
Todat there you see it? איתמר חביתי כהן גדול. Itmar chavitei kohen
gadol. כיצד עושין אותן. Keitzad osin otan.
תני תנא קמיה. Tani tana kamey. Oh we did that we did
that. No no. Okay איתמר. Itmar. חביתי כהן גדול. Chavitei kohen gadol.
כיצד עושין אותן? Keitzad osin otan? רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan אופיהן ואחר
כך מטגנה Ofeyhan ve-achar kach metagnah ורבי אסי אמר רבי חנינה Ve-Rabbi
Assi amar Rabbi Chanina מטגנה ואחר כך
אופיה. Metagnah ve-achar kach ofeyah.
So do you do the frying first or the baking first? That's
essentially what the debate is. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you
do the baking first or I should say רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
he's going to... רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya says you do the baking
first. רבי אסי Rabbi Assi says you do the frying first. Okay?
אמר רבי חייא Amar Rabbi Chiyya which is the first position רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya who says the baking first כוותי דידי מסתברא Kevati
didi mistabra תופיני תופיני נאה. tufinei tufinei na'eh.
So basically we're going to talk about this תופיני word which is
why I have to translate all this. We never see anywhere
in תורה other than here this word תופיני right? Which is to
bake. So since it's the only time it appears you know we
have a little bit of license to דרש drash it. תופיני נאה.
Tufinei na'eh. So because... so תופיני
נאה
Tufinei
na'eh.
so like you know basically it should be nice. So therefore he
says that you know that the baking would come first because if
you fry it first then the baking is not going to be
as nice. If you fry it it's going to be a little
bit charred right? So so it's not going to look as nice
when you bake it. So תופיני נאה Tufinei na'eh means it should
be you know as nice as possible when you bake it. That's
why it's baked first. רבי אסי אמר כוותי דידי מסתברא Rabbi Assi
amar kevati didi mistabra תופיני תופיני נא. Tufinei tufinei na. No
so he's saying that the frying comes first right? Because we have
this... נא Na right? From... נא Na is kind of like לא
מבושל כל צרכו lo mevushal kol tsorko the way רש"י explains it
there. So נא na means like already kind of like partially done
right? So תופיני
נאה Tufinei na'eh so bake it partially done. So what would mean...
if it's partially done by what? By frying right? So it's part
of the process. So bake it already you know after part of
the process was done. So then basically this means... so basically we
have a debate right? So which is done and they each explain
the word תופיני to support their
position okay? תופיני תופיני נא. Tufinei tufinei na. כתינאי. Ke-tannai. So this
is exactly a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. תופיני תופיני נא. Tufinei tufinei na. תופיני נאה.
Tufinei na'eh רבי אומר
Rabbi
omer תופיני תופיני נאה. Tufinei na'eh. Hold on. Yes right. So so
there're going to be three explanations. So תופיני can mean תופיני נא
Tufinei na that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. רבי Rabbi says תופיני
נאה Tufinei na'eh which is you know again each of these are
corresponding to רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya and
רבי אסי Rabbi Assi I think it was. So and then a
third position is רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer תופיני רבה tufinei
rabbah which is a completely different position. What does that mean? אית
ליה מאפה ואית ליה נא. Islei me-afve ve-islei na. So it means
he holds for both of them. So what does that mean? So
how do you have both? So רש"י gives three explanations. I'll read
it. אית ליה נא ומשום
הכי
אופה אחר טיגון ואית ליה נאה ומשום הכי אופה תחילה. Islei na
u-meshum hachi ofeh achar tigun ve-islei na'eh u-meshum hachi ofeh techila. So
basically what he holds is you do... you bake it twice. So
you bake it fry it and bake it according to this position.
Okay so that's one explanation. Another way is תופיני רבה Tufinei rabbah
גדולה. gedola. So mean תופיני רבה Tufinei rabbah so basically you make
it like big. So what does that mean? So by putting it
on the griddle you know like think of a pancake right? You
know when you move... you have like the batter you kind of
like move it here you move it there so it gets bigger
right? So
so so basically you fry it then bake it right? Because תופיני
רבה Tufinei rabbah means make it big. So you do that by
frying it where you can you know you can kind of move
the pan to get it all nice and big and then you
bake it. So the other one... that's the second explanation. The third
explanation is רכה rakah not רבה rabbah but רכה rakah that's what
it should be. So it should be like nice and soft. So
think of a donut right? You fry it in oil right? And
then you bake... no you don't bake it. Think of like a
nice you know soft donut. So you add a lot of oil
and then which makes it soft and then and then you bake
it okay? So the first explanation is baked-fried-baked then two explanations are
fried-then-baked right? The first of the... so again explanation one
is baked-fried-baked explanation two is that you make it big by frying
it where you can you know you can move the griddle around
and then bake it and the second explanation is no you fry
it in a lot of oil which makes it soft and then
you bake it okay? Fine.
Fine. תנן התם חביתי כהן גדול לישתן ואפייתן בפנים דוחות את השבת.
Tnan hatam chavitei kohen gadol lishatan va'afiyatan bifnim
dochot et hashabbat. So all this has to be done inside. The
kneading basically setting it all up and baking it has to be
done inside so you don't do this in your house and this
is done all the time inside the בית העזרה Beit Ha'azarah in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash so you don't do it inside your
house. So and דוחות את השבת dochot et hashabbat and it pushes
off the Sabbath.
So מנא הני מילי
manei
hanei milei because אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna because
תופניה, tofneha, תופניה נאה, tofneha na'eh, right? Because we just said תופניה
tofneha means make it nice. ואפילו מאתמול איפשא vi'afiyilei me'etmol ipasha because
if you bake it next day it's going to be stale, right?
So basically cooking on Sabbath, you're frying, you're baking something like that
that isn't going to be eaten in any way and then you're
going to burn it all on Sabbath. Right.
Okay. So and if you do it yes, what?
They were allowed
to do this on Sabbath in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, yeah
for... No, not at home, in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So
it has to be nice fresh bread essentially, right? Because if you
do it the day before it's not going to be so good.
מתקיף לה רב יוסף, maskif lah Rav Yosef, אימא דחביש ליה בירקא,
ima de-chavish lei be-yarqa, or you know wrap it in vegetable leaves
so it won't get so keep fresh, basically keep it fresh somehow.
Why?
I don't understand since it's not going to be eaten anyway, nobody's
going to eat it, it's going to get burnt, you allow you
to be מחלל שבת mechallel shabbat for something that you're going to
throw out just so it should look nice? Who's going to see
it? You know the...
I mean the most I can say is is גזירת הכתוב. gezeirat
hakatuv. I mean that's what the Torah's telling you.
No I know, I know but it's odd. To have the קרבן
on Sabbath you have to do it. You have to.
But this is for wasted.
It has no use.
It gets burnt. I guess it depends on what you consider as
a waste, you know what I
mean, that
would be the point of symbolism of it, what's symbolic meaning of
this ritual whatever you call it.
So they were allowed to be מחלל שבת mechallel shabbat for anything
in...
well I mean אין שבות במקדש ein shvut ba-mikdash essentially.
But
well we know they played music and all that's Sabbath too.
It's very different back then. So basically anyway the point being why
don't we find a way to preserve it? So maybe this is
their concern like why should we be מחלל שבת mechallel shabbat if
there's some way we can kind of get around it? Like you
know put it in wrap it in something so it'll stay nice
and fresh you know. So דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, de-vairabbi Yishmael tanna,
תעשה te'aseh because that's what it says over there
תעשה. te'aseh. So אפילו בשבת. afilu be-shabbat. תעשה te'aseh אפילו בטומאה. afilu
be-tumah. So אביי אמר Abaye amar so that's how he gets it
another way. אביי אמר אמר קרא תמיד Abaye amar amar kera tamid
so
תמיד tamid so כמנחת תמידין keminchat temidin right? So תמידין temidin is
offered all the time on Sabbath too. So this too it says
תמיד tamid so it has to be offered all the time. רבא
אמר על מחבת Rava amar al machavat למד שטעונה כלי limed she-te'una
k'li ואפילו מאתמול איפסולי בלינה vi'afiyilei me'etmol ipsolei be-lina and he's saying
it's more of a technical thing because we know you have to
do it on a כלי k'li and if you did it the
day before then you know we know everything that stays over a
day is already a פסול לינה pasul lina so you have to
do it that day. תניא כוותיה דרבא אמר על מחבת ומלמד שטעונה
כלי בשמן. tanya ke-vassa de-Rava amar al machavat u-melamed she-te'una k'li ba-shemen.
Okay now this is another topic. We're going to try to get
into it
because I really want to make up some ground. Where should we
be? We should have been finishing נ' א' Nun Aleph today. We
should be finishing on נ' א' Nun Aleph today. So I want
to try to get to the bottom if we can I'll try
to go you know. So basically what it says is that we
know you need you know that this thing is fried baked fried
baked scalded whatever right? Or the yeah whatever order you do it
in that was a מחלוקת machloket the order
but those were the steps over there.
So על מחבת ומלמד שטעונה כלי al machavat u-melamed she-te'una k'li right?
That's what it says. מחבת machavat is the that's what it is
right? The מחבת machvat is this thing you bake it in. בשמן
ba-shemen להוסיף לה שמן le-hosif lah shemen to add oil. So basically
we're saying what are your proportions? איני יודע כמה. eini yodeia kamma.
How much oil? הרי אני דן נאמר כאן שמן נאמר להלן במנחת
נסכים שמן. harei ani dan ne'emar kan shemen ne'emar le-halan be-minchat nesachim
shemen. So we know that but they're kind what are our analogs?
So the תמידין temidin came with this came with a מנחה minchah
and we also know that you can offer a מנחה minchah as
a נדבה nedavah right? But the proportion of oil are different. So
with the תמידין temidin you have מה להלן שלשה לוגין לעשרון ma
le-halan sheloshah lugin le-isaron it was three לוגין lugin of שמן shemen
for each עשרון isaron אף כאן שלשה לוגין לעשרון. af kan sheloshah
lugin le-isaron. Maybe over here this חביתין chavitin, will be three לוגין.
lugin. או כלך לדרך זו o kalach laderach zu נאמר כאן שמן
נאמר במנחת נדבה שמן. ne'emar kan shemen ne'emar be-minchat nedavah shemen. So
we know over here again this is done in oil and with
the voluntary מנחה minchah offering you know over there also there's oil.
מה להלן לוג אחד אף כאן לוג אחד. ma le-halan log echad
af kan log echad.
So that was one לוג. log. So if you look at it
from a
תמיד tamid perspective you're going to offer three לוגין lugin of oil.
If you compare it to a נדבה nedavah you offer one לוג
log of oil. So which one is it? Do you offer three
or one? So נבא ללמוד. nava lilmod. נימא לתמיד דומה, nima letamid
domeh, what is it like?
דנין denin תב"ת, tavat,
I'm going to,
it's really תב"ת tavat or תש"ט, tashat, whatever, מתש"ט, me-tashat, תדיר tadir
is the ת, taf, then דוחה
שבת,
docheh shabbat,
that's a ש, shin, and דוחה טומאה, docheh tumah, right? Because we
know that all these things are
true, you bring it all the time, you bring it even on
שבת, shabbat, and even if everyone is טמא, tamei, you're still bringing
it. And so basically this is true for the תמידין, temidin, right?
It's always offered, and it's true for the חביתין, chavitin right? So
maybe it's compared that way.
So there's ואי דנין תש"ט משאינו תש"ט, ve-ee denin tashat me-she-eino tashat,
right? So compare it basically to look at those three things in
common. או כלך לדרך זו, o kalech lederech zu, דנין יחיד מיחיד,
denin yachid mi-yachid, meaning יחיד, yachid, right? This is brought by the
כהן, it's not a communal sacrifice so to speak, and it's בגלל
עצמה biglal atzmah ולבונה. ve-levonah. And you know, and it's brought on
its own, meaning this חביתין chavitin. is not brought with an animal,
right? You just bring it. And also you bring it with לבונה.
levonah. ואין דנין יחיד משאינו יחיד. ve-ein denin yachid me-she-eino yachid.
So don't compare it to the תמיד tamid because the תמיד tamid
is communal sacrifice, all these things are different, right? So basically which
way do you compare it to? You have three ways of comparing
it to one thing, three ways of comparing it to another. So
at the end of the day we don't know, right? So רבי
שמעון בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר, Rabbi Shimon beno shel
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, סולת מנחה תמיד. solet minchah tamid. No,
it says סולת מנחה תמיד, solet minchah tamid, הרי הוא כמנחת תמידין.
harei hu ke-minchat temidin. מה מנחת תמידין שלשה לוגין עשרון אף זו
שלשה לוגין עשרון. ma minchat temidin sheloshah lugin isaron af zu sheloshah
lugin isaron. So basically that's the answer, right? So we had a
question, which way do you go? You can go one way if
you compare it to a תמיד, tamid, so compare it to a
תמיד. tamid. You have all these other ways like it's a יחיד
yachid and therefore should be compared to a נדבה nedavah or voluntary
offering. I don't know. So רבי שמעון בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקה Rabbi Shimon beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says let me
just look at the פסוק, pasuk it says סולת מנחה תמיד, solet
minchah tamid, right? It says that in there, תמיד, tamid, right? So
just like a תמיד tamid is done with three לוגין lugin of
oil, so too should this be done with three לוגין lugin of
oil. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, ריבה כאן שמן ריבה במנחת
כבשים שמן. riba kan shemen riba be-minchat kevasim shemen. מה להלן שלשה
לוגין עשרון אף כאן שלשה לוגין עשרון. ma lohalan sheloshah lugin isaron
af kan sheloshah lugin isaron.
So he says alright, again he's going to go through like another
way of looking at it but come up with the same conclusion.
He says okay, look, it says בשמן, bashemen, we just start out
by saying you have to add oil, how much is it? Do
we do three לוגין lugin just like we do by the תמיד?
tamid? או כלך לדרך זו, o kalech lederech zu, ריבה כאן שמן
ריבה במנחת פרים ואילים שמן. riba kan shemen riba be-minchat parim ve-eilim
shemen. We know so
okay look, you're comparing it to a כבש. keves. A כבש keves
comes with three לוגין. lugin. But wait, hold on, there are also
פרים, parim, there are also אילים. eilim. מה להלן שני לוגין עשרון
אף כאן שני לוגין עשרון, ma lohalan shenei lugin isaron af kan
shenei lugin isaron, right?
So who says you should compare it to a lamb, right? This
is a flour after all. If you compare it to a lamb
it's three, if you compare it to a what's it called, if
you compare it to a ram then it's two. So which way
do you go? We know you have to use because בשמן bashemen
means you have to use more, so it's not just going to
be one לוג, log, it has to be more. So is it
more as in a lamb which would be three or is it
more as in a ram which would be two?
נימא למי דומה? nima le-mi domeh? דנין מנחה הבאה בעשרון ממנחה הבאה
בעשרון.
denin minchah ha-ba'ah be-isaron mi-minchah
ha-ba'ah be-isaron. ואין דנין מנחה הבאה בעשרון ממנחה הבאה בב' וג' עשרונים.
ve-ein denin minchah ha-ba'ah be-isaron mi-minchah ha-ba'ah bi-ve ve-ge esronim. Now again
if
you remember your שלושה
עשרונים לפר, sheloshah esronim la-par, שני עשרונים לאיל, shenei esronim la-ayil, all
these kind of things. So
basically if you look at the proportions, it fits in with the
proportion for the lamb, right? The proportions of oil versus flour for
the rams are just not the same as the one for the
חביתין. So therefore if you want to keep proportionality intact, you're going
to offer three לוגין. lugin. I just simplified that. So then give
me, I, we can get to the דף daf below, I already
did all this, it just took two minutes. So what? So basically
yeah, so I mean I hope everyone's with me. So basically we
have two different ways of getting to the same conclusion, right? So
basically one way is just looking at it from the פסוק, right?
We had a question, do you do three versus one? We said
you do three because it says תמיד, tamid, just like the תמיד
tamid is three, this also is three. Or we had another way
of looking at it that we know you have to do more,
do you compare it to the כבש keves which is three or
do you compare it to the איל ayil which is two? Well,
compare it to the כבש keves because the proportionality would be the
same if you just keep it that way, okay? All right, so
now we said wait a minute, so we started out by saying
להוסיף לו שמן, lehosif lo shemen, which means you add a bunch
of
oil, which would be three. Then we said oh maybe compare it
to נדבה nedavah which is one. Wait, what do you mean? So
that's kind of self-contradictory. אגופא קשיא, agufa kashya, אמרת בשמן להוסיף לו
שמן. amarta bashemen lehosif lo shemen. ואמרת נאמר כאן שמן ונאמר במנחת
נדבה שמן. ve-amarta ne'emar kan shemen ve-ne'emar be-minchat nedavah shemen. So either
if
so it's not a lot of oil, just doing one, one is
the minimum, right? And here you're saying להוסיף לו שמן, lehosif lo
shemen, you have to add on like a bunch of oil, right?
So which is it, right? So don't you know so אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, מאן תנא בשמן להוסיף? man tanna bashemen lehosif? רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. So basically what we're trying to say is that and
It's going to be a little confusing, and none of these are
actually going to be like it just doesn't sound this way, but
we're trying to say like who's saying what, right? Because we're trying
to understand, like I don't understand, you seem to be contradicting yourself.
So again we had this, seems like there was a תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, then you had רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, then you had
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So now what we're really saying is that
although it seems that you know that they're only coming in their
places, really רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon comes in, again it's like
nobody, רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So really רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is coming in the beginning. So it's רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And
this is how it's going. So it's really רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
So basically what he wanted to do is like, oh I understand.
So
basically what he's saying is 'oh, maybe I don't add a lot
of oil.' Then he's like 'well, let's see, can we figure out
logically?' Which is why he started going that way. So logically he
wouldn't add, you know, would you compare it to something? So that's
how it's ודינה מאן קמהדר u-deina man kam-hadar רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is saying 'Okay,
you know, now you had your question, I'm going to answer it.'
So רב הונא בריה דרבי יהושע אמר כולה רבי שמעון, Rav Huna
berei de-Rabbi Yehoshua amar kulei Rabbi Shimon, בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא. beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka. It's really all of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So even though he comes in second, he really
should like, you know, put him from second to first. So he's
saying first and second. Does that make sense?
So basically he's saying הכי קאמר, בשמן להוסיף שמן. hachi ka-amar ba-shemen
lehosif shemen.
To add oil, because דאי קבע שמן לא צריך, de-ee ke-va shemen
lo tzarich, כיון דכתיב על המחבת. keivan de-chtiv al ha-machvat. It means
you have to add a certain amount because if it's used to
oil to begin with, you don't need to say במחבת בשמן. ba-machvat
ba-shemen. מחבת machvat by definition is with שמן. shemen. Because we know
that you know because that's what it is. מחבת machvat is a
frying pan, and obviously you're not going to fry, you're not going
to put it in a frying pan and not use oil. You're
frying it in a frying pan. So
כיון דכתיב על המחבת, keivan de-chtiv al ha-machvat, כעין מחבת דמי. ke-ein
machvat dami. We know that since it says על המחבת, al ha-machvat,
then you don't need to say בשמן, ba-shemen, right? Because מחבת machvat,
means it's done on this frying pan. So it doesn't mean to
add oil. So since it says בשמן, ba-shemen, since you do have
an extra word בשמן, ba-shemen, it means to add שמן. shemen. So
now we're going to try to think about 'oh maybe אינו אלא
לקבוע לו שמן'
eino ela likboa
lo
shemen to teach you that you have to have שמן. shemen. דאי
לא כתב רחמנא בשמן, de-ee lo chtiv Rachmana ba-shemen, הוה אמינא תיהוי
כמין חרבות. hava amina teihavei kemin charvot. Maybe it would be just
placed on the מחבת, machvat, just like a חרבות charvot is not
used with oil. It's not put on a מחבת, machvat but you
know, whatever. But maybe because we know some מנחות menachot are offered
without oil, maybe it just means you just put it on the
מחבת but don't fry it. Why you would do that I don't
know. Therefore בשמן ba-shemen means you actually use oil. And now we
don't know how much. And that's why you get into this whole
thing, you compare it to one or three and that's what that
part is. Okay. הדר אמר תבני מנחת תמיד ודינה ודן דינא ולא
אתא ליה ואיצטריך קרא. hadar amar tivnei minchat tamid ve-deina ve-dan deina
ve-lo ata lei ve-itztarich kra. So then he's like 'oh, let's see,
can we figure out logically?' He wasn't able to because you can
go compare it to a תמיד tamid or you can compare it
to נדבה. nedava. And therefore he ended up looking at the פסוק
which was a תמיד. tamid. Okay. Last part. ואיצטריך קרא וסמך כרבי
ישמעאל מילתא. ve-itztarich kra ve-samach ke-Rabbi Yishmael milta.
Just like he finished it up. Now רבא אמר כולה רבי שמעון,
Rava amar kulei Rabbi Shimon, right?
It's all רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and this is how it works.
הכי קאמר hachi ka-amar, בשמן להוסיף שמן. ba-shemen lehosif shemen. דאי קבע
לשמן לא צריך כיון דכתיב על המחבת. de-ee ke-va le-shemen lo tzarich
keivan de-chtiv al ha-machvat. Same thing. So we know בשמן ba-shemen means
you have to add more oil because if it's to use oil,
we wouldn't need you to tell me that because it says על
המחבת. al ha-machvat. ואי שלא יאמר בשמן הייתי אומר בדין. ve-ee shelo
yomar ba-shemen haiti omer be-din. Oh, he's like 'Wait a minute. Hmm.
Now maybe I don't even need the בשמן. ba-shemen. Maybe I can
figure out logically how much to use.' And then he goes through
all that. You compare it to one or three. But then he's
like ודן דינא ולא אתא ליה. ve-dan deina ve-lo ata lei.
So then he wanted to compare it logically, but he wasn't able
to because you can go one way or the other, you can
go three versus one. ואיצטריך בשמן. ve-itztarich ba-shemen.
So
you need this בשמן. ba-shemen. And then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon kind
of like just interjects himself in there. And הדר אמר תיתי ממנחת
פרים ואילים. hadar amar teitei mi-minchat parim ve-eilim. He's like 'Oh, wait
a minute. Well, all right, fine. I can't you know, I don't
know if I should compare it to the תמיד. tamid. I don't
know if I should compare it to the יחיד.' yachid. Then he's
like 'Oh wait, maybe I can compare it to the פרים ואילים
parim ve-eilim which were two.' Then הדר אמר דנין מנחה הבאה עם
הנסכים. hadar amar danin mincha ha-ba'ah im ha-nesachim. Then he ends up
with this conclusion. So basically I mean again, like you know, we
never changed our conclusion. We just wanted to know who said the
first part, that's all. And then we said it can go a
number of ways. It can either be רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And then we tried to organize how the
rest of it flows. But if you got lost in that, it's
not too important because that didn't really change anything.
All right, we did, we did a whole דף daf actually today.
Yeah, we did a whole דף daf today.
So we're going until two, two.
He has to go to a meeting.